Curriculum Vitae

Biodata



Ricardo Jorge de Araújo Ferreira

Electrical and Computer Science Engineer (M.Sc.)
Student of Master in Informatics and Computing Engineering

Rua Conde de Ferreira 97, 4°D 4580 - 407 Paredes Paredes, Portugal ricarraf@gmail.com
ricardojaferreira
// RicardoAraujoFerreira

January 19, 1985

 \Box +351 91 615 15 65

Summary

I obtained my master degree in Electrical and Computer science Engineering at the Faculdade de Engenharia da Universidade do Porto, Portugal in 2008. My master thesis was in the field of Power electronics, control drives and measurement techniques, resulting in a group of power converters to be used in a solar Electric Car.

Since then I have been trying to acquire experience and pursuing challenging job opportunities. For 3,5 years I have worked at Efacec, SA, as a control/automation engineer. At first my main activity was the development of automation and telecontrol solutions for electric power systems. When I acquired more experience I have started training new employees and to manage engineering projects, coordinate teams, allocate resources, supervising and find ways to improve processes and reduce the developing time.

When a new opportunity arose at the Institute for Systems and Computer Science of Porto to integrate the renewable energies team I took it. At this job, as a researcher in the field of power converters for electric vehicles and intelligent power grids, I have increased my technical and planning skills. I had also the opportunity to write scientific papers and to present them on international conferences. Being an R&D engineer was a great opportunity to go out of my comfort zone and to test new and challenging areas. During this job I found out that I really love to develop software.

I started to develop some tiny softwares to help on my everyday tasks, applications running on the web and locally, that perform data analysis, file creation and manipulation, integration with databases and others. And some applications just to learn and have fun.

Sometime later, I started to work has a developer and I am working on that area since then. I am currently working has a full stack developer in an Agile (scrum) environment with technologies like, Javascript, PHP, MySqI, Java, Apache Servers, AWS, Git, integration with APIs, and others.

To learn more about software development, algorithms and new programming languages, I have started the **Master Degree in Informatics and Computing Engineering** at Faculdade de Engenharia, I am currently at the 4rd year out of a 5 year program.

Work Experience

Web Engineer - Fullstack Developer

July 2018 - Present

Jumia - Porto Tech Center

Porto, Portugal

- Development of software solutions using PHP and JAVA frameworks;
- Technical Specification and development of business requirements and improvements;
- Integration with third party softwares and tools;
- Development of solutions with a strong concern about clean code and architecture.

Fullstack Developer

Feb 2018 - July 2018

7Skin, Lda (E-Commerce)

Porto, Portugal

- Development and integration of software solutions, client/sever programming (PHP, Javascript, SQL, CSS, HTML5);
- Development of internal software to improve processes and reduce operation times (PHP and Web Technologies);
- Database management and maintenance (MySQL);
- User interface and usability development and improvement;
- Integration with external services (REST and other API's);
- Support to other teams and development of custom solutions.

Fullstack Developer

May 2014 - Feb 2018

Gravity Demand, Lda (E-Commerce)

Penafiel, Portugal

- Development and integration of software solutions, client/sever programming (JAVA, PHP, Javascript, SQL, CSS, HTML5);
- User interface and usability development and improvement;
- Integration with external services (REST and other API's);
- Technical specification, design and architecture;
- Management of the e-commerce platform;
- Management and coordination between work teams (Marketing, Design, Sales, Development).

R&D Engineer

Jan. 2012 - May. 2014

INESC, Institute for Systems and Computer Engineering

Porto, Portugal

- Research, testing and development of power converters for electric vehicles and power grids;
- Design of analog and digital feedback control systems (Software and hardware);
- Validate emerging concepts in Smart-Grids and Renewable Energy systems by developing electronic prototypes;
- Coordination and planning of the activities and resources for the development laboratories;
- Development of software for validating concepts and make complex computations (C++ and JAVA).

Control and Automation Engineer, Junior manager

Aug. 2008 - Jan. 2012

Efacec, Sistemas de Engenharia SA

Maia, Portugal

- Development of control and automation architectures for the Portuguese electric power system (Distribution and Transport Substations - 15kW to 400kW);
- Commissioning and development of factory and site acceptance tests for electric power systems;
- Management and configuration of large IP based Networks and information systems based on UNIX platforms;
- Management of engineering projects (Planning Schedules and coordinate activities).

FEUP Project

FEUP, Porto

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

Sept. 2007 - Jan. 2008

- Teach how to organize and develop an engineering project.
- Led weekly course seminars.

Education

MsC in Informatics and Computation Engineering

Present

Faculdade de Engenharia da Universidade do Porto

Porto, Portugal

- Currently at the 4rd Year, 2 more to finish the graduation.
- Principal Subjects so far:
 - * Languages and Web Technologies; Computation Theory; Algorithms; Discreet Mathematics, Oriented Programming Languages, Operating Systems, Databases

MsC in Electrical and Computers Engineering

2008

Faculdade de Engenharia da Universidade do Porto

Porto, Portugal

- Major: Automation and Control Systems
- Specialization: Power and Industrial Electronics and Instrumentation
- Thesis: Solar Car. (Classified with 17 out of 20)

Languages

(Scale: 1 - Basic, 5 - Very Good)

Portuguese 5 (Mother Tongue)
Italian 5 (My Father is Italian)

English 5 (Obtained the international C1 Level)

Spanish 3

* Skills

- Programming and Markup Languages
 - Expert: JAVA, CSS, HTML5, JSON, SQL, PHP, JavaScript, C/C++, LATEX
 - Intermediate: Python, XML, C#, Pascal, Visual Basic

- Frameworks
 - Expert: Play, Zend, Bootstrap, LESS
 - Intermediate: Spring, Laravel, Node.Js, Angular
- Test and Debug
 - Junit, PHPunit, Xdebug
- Tools and Software
 - Expert: UNIX Shell, Docker, MongoDb, Elastic Search, Prometheus, Grafana, MySQL/MariaDb, Apache 2, Magento, GIT
 - Intermediate: PostgreSQL, Couchbase, RabbitMQ, Nginx
- Operating Systems
 - Mac OS X, Linux, Microsoft Windows
- Social
 - People person, enjoys being challenged, hardworking, leadership, entrepreneurial, organized.

Zi a de fouge de Anaige Connelle